export const JambCrs = [
  {
    question:
      "The brother of David who got angry when he heard David speaking with the men to enquire about what the king would do to any man that was able to kill Goliath was",
    options: ["Ozem", "Abinadab", "Raddai", "Eliab"],
    answer: "Eliab",
  },
  {
    question: "The meaning of Beelzebub is",
    options: [
      "The prince of demons",
      "The power of the devil",
      "The god of Baal",
      "The overcomer of the devil",
    ],
    answer: "The power of the devil",
  },
  {
    question: "The story of the healing of the paralytic shows that Jesus",
    options: [
      "Is a healer",
      "Has the authority to forgive sins",
      "Has power over demons",
      "Is highly compassionate",
    ],
    answer: "Has the authority to forgive sins",
  },
  {
    question: "Saul, the first king of Israel, was from the tribe of",
    options: ["Gad", "Manasseh", "Judah", "Benjamin"],
    answer: "Benjamin",
  },
  {
    question: "The parable that is peculiar to Luke in the following is",
    options: [
      "The foolish man",
      "The lost sheep",
      "The man without a wedding garment",
      "The mustard seed and the leaven",
    ],
    answer: "The man without a wedding garment",
  },
  {
    question:
      "_____ was the name of the prophet who rebuked King David for having seized Uriah's wife",
    options: ["Hosea", "Elisha", "Nathan", "Amos"],
    answer: "Nathan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the greatest achievements of King David as king over Israel was his capture of Jerusalem for the purpose of",
    options: [
      "Making it his political and religious centre",
      "Avenging the death of Jonathan his best friend",
      "Making the Jebusites respect him",
      "Providing shelter for his subjects",
    ],
    answer: "Making it his political and religious centre",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following made King Josiah popular?",
    options: [
      "Excellent communication",
      "Trade decrees",
      "Religious reforms",
      "Victories in battles",
    ],
    answer: "Religious reforms",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following thought he could obtain the gift of God with money?",
    options: ["Elymas", "Simon", "Ananias", "Demetrius"],
    answer: "Simon",
  },
  {
    question: "The man regarded as the founder of the Israelite religion is",
    options: ["Moses", "Abraham", "Josiah", "Joshua"],
    answer: "Moses",
  },
  {
    question: "Why did Pharaoh Neco put Jehoahaz in bonds?",
    options: [
      "Neco regarded him as a threat to his kingdom",
      "Jehoahaz refused to pay tribute to Neco",
      "Jehoahaz did what was evil in the sight of the Lord",
      "Neco did not want him to reign in Jerusalem",
    ],
    answer: "Neco did not want him to reign in Jerusalem",
  },
  {
    question: "The first council on the issue of circumcision was held at",
    options: ["Antioch", "Judea", "Jerusalem", "Lystra"],
    answer: "Jerusalem",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following parables depicts God's love for all men?",
    options: [
      "The mustard seed",
      "The ten maids",
      "The sower",
      "The prodigal son",
    ],
    answer: "The prodigal son",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is the special interest of the Gospel of Luke?",
    options: [
      "The spiritual nature of Jews",
      "Stories about lepers",
      "The universality of the Gospel",
      "None of the above",
    ],
    answer: "The universality of the Gospel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After the Israelites had divided the land by casting lots, which city was given to Joshua?",
    options: ["Timnath-serah", "Ekron", "Zorah", "Elon"],
    answer: "Timnath-serah",
  },
  {
    question: "What did Solomon do to maintain his harem?",
    options: [
      "He collected donations from the neighbouring states",
      "He built warehouses",
      "He took money from the temple treasury",
      "He taxed his people heavily",
    ],
    answer: "He taxed his people heavily",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following prophets assisted Ezekiel with prayers?",
    options: ["Elijah", "Isaiah", "Hosea", "Elisha"],
    answer: "Isaiah",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the father of John the Baptist?",
    options: ["Zebedee", "Simeon", "Zachariah", "Achim"],
    answer: "Zachariah",
  },
  {
    question: "King Solomon got timber for his building from",
    options: ["Beersheba", "Lebanon", "Egypt", "Jerusalem"],
    answer: "Lebanon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The last miracle God performed before the Israelites were released was",
    options: [
      "The slaughter of the first born",
      "The pollution of the Nile",
      "The slaughter of all the male children",
      "The plague of locusts",
    ],
    answer: "The slaughter of the first born",
  },
  {
    question: "Paul and Silas were imprisoned at",
    options: ["Antioch", "Athens", "Philippi", "Ephesus"],
    answer: "Philippi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'You would bring down my grey hairs with sorrow to Sheol'. Jacob said this to his children because",
    options: [
      "Joseph was unjustly imprisoned",
      "Joseph had been reported killed",
      "The famine was very severe",
      "He feared that Benjamin would be lost to him like Joseph",
    ],
    answer: "He feared that Benjamin would be lost to him like Joseph",
  },
  {
    question:
      "King Solomon was not supposed to have married foreign women because",
    options: [
      "The women of Israel were more beautiful",
      "They would entice him to worship idols",
      "They were very jealous",
      "A king should not have too many children",
    ],
    answer: "They would entice him to worship idols",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was Saul publicly made king before the Lord and all the people of Israel?",
    options: ["Gilgal", "Mizpah", "Bethel", "Dan"],
    answer: "Gilgal",
  },
  {
    question: "The signs of the end were prophesied by",
    options: ["Amos", "Jeremiah", "Daniel", "Malachi"],
    answer: "Daniel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'I have no silver and gold, but I give you what I have, in the name of Jesus Christ of Nazareth, walk.' This was said by Peter to a lame man",
    options: [
      "At the pool called Bethesda",
      "At the gate called Beautiful",
      "Carried by four friends",
      "Who was also blind",
    ],
    answer: "At the gate called Beautiful",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The message of the risen Christ to the women who came early to the tomb was to be relayed to the disciples and to",
    options: ["The Jews", "Peter", "Thomas", "The Sadducees"],
    answer: "Peter",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Mark's Gospel, what was the first miracle performed by Jesus?",
    options: [
      "Healing a leper",
      "Opening the eyes of a blind man",
      "Raising a dead boy to life",
      "Healing a man with an unclean spirit",
    ],
    answer: "Healing a man with an unclean spirit",
  },
  {
    question: "Justification by grace shows that work is",
    options: [
      "Opposed to salvation",
      "Complementary to grace",
      "The primary condition for salvation",
      "Not required for salvation",
    ],
    answer: "Not required for salvation",
  },
  {
    question: "The importance of love in the teachings of Peter is that it",
    options: [
      "Brings together all believers in the community",
      "Covers a multitude of sins",
      "Takes one to eternal life",
      "Extends to Christians only",
    ],
    answer: "Covers a multitude of sins",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Peter urges Christians to live as free men without necessarily using their freedom as a pretext for",
    options: ["Evil", "Immorality", "Partiality", "Greed"],
    answer: "Evil",
  },
  {
    question: "The gifts offered to Jesus at his birth by the wise men were",
    options: [
      "Gold, Frankincense and Myrrh",
      "Myrrh, Gold and Frankincense",
      "Silver, Myrrh and Silver",
      "Gold, Silver and Frankincense",
    ],
    answer: "Gold, Frankincense and Myrrh",
  },
  {
    question: "God did not allow David to build the temple because",
    options: [
      "He had committed murder",
      "The people did not want him to build the temple",
      "The land was polluted",
      "He did not have sufficient materials",
    ],
    answer: "He had committed murder",
  },
  {
    question: "Why did Jesus decide to go to the wilderness after his baptism?",
    options: [
      "To be tempted by Satan",
      "To gather disciples",
      "To meditate",
      "To spread the gospel",
    ],
    answer: "To be tempted by Satan",
  },
  {
    question: "The parable of the good Samaritan teaches",
    options: [
      "Showing mercy to others",
      "Helping travelers",
      "Following God’s commandments",
      "Assisting the poor",
    ],
    answer: "Showing mercy to others",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the prophet that anointed David as king?",
    options: ["Nathan", "Samuel", "Ezekiel", "Elisha"],
    answer: "Samuel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the Parable of the Talents, the servant given one talent was reprimanded for",
    options: [
      "Spending the talent",
      "Burying the talent",
      "Investing in a risky venture",
      "Giving the talent to another servant",
    ],
    answer: "Burying the talent",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who helped Moses lift up his hands during the battle with Amalek?",
    options: ["Joshua", "Hur and Aaron", "Miriam and Hur", "Aaron and Joshua"],
    answer: "Hur and Aaron",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Joseph called the name of his first born Manasseh, meaning God has _____",
    options: [
      "made him forget his hardship and his father’s house",
      "made him fruitful in the land of his affliction",
      "rescued him from the hands of Potiphar",
      "made him not to forget his brothers and his household",
    ],
    answer: "made him forget his hardship and his father’s house",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…Now therefore lighten the hard service of your father upon us, and we will serve you.” This request was made to Rehoboam because _____",
    options: [
      "the people had another person in mind",
      "the people wanted to test his wisdom",
      "of an impending revolt",
      "the people wanted some relief",
    ],
    answer: "the people wanted some relief",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“You are the man…” This statement by Nathan made David immediately _____",
    options: [
      "order him out of the palace",
      "order the killing of the child",
      "confess and ask for forgiveness",
      "abdicate his throne",
    ],
    answer: "confess and ask for forgiveness",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the consequences of Saul’s disobedience was that _____",
    options: [
      "the Philistines killed him",
      "he killed himself",
      "the Amalekites killed him",
      "his armour bearer killed him",
    ],
    answer: "he killed himself",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…The Lord will fight for you, and you have only to be still.” This statement was made by Moses when the _____",
    options: [
      "Egyptians were pursuing the Israelites before the Red Sea",
      "Israelites were standing before Joshua",
      "Israelites were standing before King Pharaoh",
      "Israelites’ chariots were crossing the Red Sea",
    ],
    answer: "Egyptians were pursuing the Israelites before the Red Sea",
  },
  {
    question:
      "God told Solomon that He would surely tear the kingdom from him and give it to his _____",
    options: ["son", "brother", "servant", "army commander"],
    answer: "servant",
  },
  {
    question: "Why did Joab kill Abner?",
    options: [
      "He wanted to avenge the death of his brother",
      "He feared that Abner would take over his post",
      "Abner only came to deceive David",
      "He was an enemy who came to spy on David",
    ],
    answer: "He wanted to avenge the death of his brother",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When God told Abraham that Sarah would have a child, Abraham laughed because _____",
    options: [
      "he already had a child by Hagar",
      "his wife Sarah was barren",
      "his wife was too old to have a child",
      "he was amused by the promise",
    ],
    answer: "his wife was too old to have a child",
  },
  {
    question: "In the beginning, God created the _____",
    options: [
      "heavens and the earth",
      "animals and the birds",
      "light and the darkness",
      "water and the dry land",
    ],
    answer: "heavens and the earth",
  },
  {
    question: "Moses fled Egypt to the land of Midian because _____",
    options: [
      "he was afraid that his crime would be made known",
      "Pharaoh wanted to kill him for the crime he had committed",
      "his countryman asked if he would also kill him",
      "he had killed an Egyptian and buried him in the sand",
    ],
    answer: "Pharaoh wanted to kill him for the crime he had committed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The LORD sent Samuel to Saul to go and destroy the Amalekites because _____",
    options: [
      "they opposed Israel on their way out of Egypt",
      "they were idolaters",
      "they disobeyed God",
      "their land had been given to Israel after the battle",
    ],
    answer: "they opposed Israel on their way out of Egypt",
  },
  {
    question: "In the creation story, man was permitted to _____",
    options: [
      "plant fruit trees for food",
      "water the garden",
      "make garments of skin",
      "name all the creatures",
    ],
    answer: "name all the creatures",
  },
  {
    question: "God instructed Moses on Mount Sinai to _____",
    options: [
      "speak to the rock",
      "strike the rock",
      "consecrate the people",
      "pray for the people",
    ],
    answer: "speak to the rock",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace…” The statement above portrays Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego as _____",
    options: [
      "men of faith",
      "disillusioned men",
      "stubborn men",
      "men with pride",
    ],
    answer: "men of faith",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Prophet Ezekiel described the house of Israel as having a hard forehead and stubborn heart because the people _____",
    options: [
      "lacked confidence in him",
      "refused to listen to him",
      "had taken God for granted",
      "had endured suffering",
    ],
    answer: "refused to listen to him",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“And the LORD God appointed a plant, and made it come up over Jonah…” The statement above taught Jonah that _____",
    options: [
      "the repentance of the Ninevites would be short-lived",
      "God is sovereign",
      "his assignment would not last long",
      "God is merciful",
    ],
    answer: "God is sovereign",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Why is your spirit so vexed that you eat no food?” The addressee was sad because _____",
    options: [
      "Naboth refused to give him his vineyard",
      "he had an encounter with Elijah",
      "his inheritance had been taken away",
      "Jezebel refused to speak to him",
    ],
    answer: "Naboth refused to give him his vineyard",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Isaiah teaches that the LORD wants His people to demonstrate holiness by _____",
    options: [
      "observing religious festivals",
      "offering more sacrifices",
      "doing justice and not evil",
      "honoring their father and mother",
    ],
    answer: "doing justice and not evil",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Joseph called the name of his first born Manasseh, meaning God has _____",
    options: [
      "made him forget his hardship and his father’s house.",
      "made him fruitful in the land of his affliction.",
      "rescued him from the hands of Potiphar.",
      "made him not to forget his brothers and his household.",
    ],
    answer: "made him forget his hardship and his father’s house.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…Now therefore lighten the hard service of your father upon us, and we will serve you.” This request was made to Rehoboam because _____",
    options: [
      "the people had another person in mind.",
      "the people wanted to test his wisdom.",
      "of an impending revolt.",
      "the people wanted some relief.",
    ],
    answer: "the people wanted some relief.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“You are the man…” This statement by Nathan made David immediately _____",
    options: [
      "order him out of the palace.",
      "order the killing of the child.",
      "confess and ask for forgiveness.",
      "abdicate his throne.",
    ],
    answer: "confess and ask for forgiveness.",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the consequences of Saul’s disobedience was that _____",
    options: [
      "the Philistines killed him.",
      "he killed himself.",
      "the Amalekites killed him.",
      "his armour bearer killed him.",
    ],
    answer: "he killed himself.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…The Lord will fight for you, and you have only to be still.” This statement was made by Moses when the _____",
    options: [
      "Egyptians were pursuing the Israelites before the Red Sea.",
      "Israelites were standing before Joshua.",
      "Israelites were standing before King Pharaoh.",
      "Israelites’ chariots were crossing the Red Sea.",
    ],
    answer: "Egyptians were pursuing the Israelites before the Red Sea.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "God told Solomon that He would surely tear the kingdom from him and give it to his _____",
    options: ["son", "brother", "servant", "army commander"],
    answer: "servant",
  },
  {
    question: "Why did Joab kill Abner?",
    options: [
      "He wanted to avenge the death of his brother.",
      "He feared that Abner would take over his post.",
      "Abner only came to deceive David.",
      "He was an enemy who came to spy on David.",
    ],
    answer: "He wanted to avenge the death of his brother.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When God told Abraham that Sarah would have a child, Abraham laughed because _____",
    options: [
      "he already had a child by Hagar.",
      "his wife Sarah was barren.",
      "his wife was too old to have a child.",
      "he was amused by the promise.",
    ],
    answer: "his wife was too old to have a child.",
  },
  {
    question: "In the beginning, God created the _____",
    options: [
      "heavens and the earth.",
      "animals and the birds.",
      "light and the darkness.",
      "water and the dry land.",
    ],
    answer: "heavens and the earth.",
  },
  {
    question: "Moses fled Egypt to the land of Midian because _____",
    options: [
      "he was afraid that his crime would be made known.",
      "Pharaoh wanted to kill him for the crime he had committed.",
      "his countryman asked if he would also kill him.",
      "he had killed an Egyptian and buried him in the sand.",
    ],
    answer: "Pharaoh wanted to kill him for the crime he had committed.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The LORD sent Samuel to Saul to go and destroy the Amalekites because _____",
    options: [
      "they opposed Israel on their way out of Egypt.",
      "they were idolaters.",
      "they disobeyed God.",
      "their land had been given to Israel after the battle.",
    ],
    answer: "they opposed Israel on their way out of Egypt.",
  },
  {
    question: "In the creation story, man was permitted to _____",
    options: [
      "plant fruit trees for food.",
      "water the garden.",
      "make garments of skin.",
      "name all the creatures.",
    ],
    answer: "name all the creatures.",
  },
  {
    question: "God instructed Moses on Mount Sinai to _____",
    options: [
      "speak to the rock.",
      "strike the rock.",
      "consecrate the people.",
      "pray for the people.",
    ],
    answer: "speak to the rock.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…If it be so, our God whom we serve is able to deliver us from the burning fiery furnace…” The statement above portrays Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego as _____",
    options: [
      "men of faith.",
      "disillusioned men.",
      "stubborn men.",
      "men with pride.",
    ],
    answer: "men of faith.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Prophet Ezekiel described the house of Israel as having a hard forehead and stubborn heart because the people _____",
    options: [
      "lacked confidence in him.",
      "refused to listen to him.",
      "had taken God for granted.",
      "had endured suffering.",
    ],
    answer: "refused to listen to him.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“And the LORD God appointed a plant, and made it come up over Jonah…” The statement above taught Jonah that _____",
    options: [
      "the repentance of the Ninevites would be short-lived.",
      "God is sovereign.",
      "his assignment would not last long.",
      "God is merciful.",
    ],
    answer: "God is sovereign.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Why is your spirit so vexed that you eat no food?” The addressee was sad because _____",
    options: [
      "Naboth refused to give him his vineyard.",
      "he had an encounter with Elijah.",
      "his inheritance had been taken away.",
      "Jezebel refused to speak to him.",
    ],
    answer: "Naboth refused to give him his vineyard.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Isaiah teaches that the LORD wants His people to demonstrate holiness by _____",
    options: [
      "observing religious festivals.",
      "offering more sacrifices.",
      "doing justice and not evil.",
      "honoring their father and mother.",
    ],
    answer: "doing justice and not evil.",
  },
  {
    question: "One of the reforms of King Josiah was that _____",
    options: [
      "he worshipped at the brook Kidron.",
      "he defiled Topheth in the valley of the sons of Hinnom.",
      "he allowed the worship of Asherah.",
      "the priests were allowed to worship in the temple.",
    ],
    answer: "he defiled Topheth in the valley of the sons of Hinnom.",
  },
  {
    question: "The main lesson of Hosea’s teachings is that God _____",
    options: [
      "will pour His spirit on all flesh.",
      "accepts every free-will offering.",
      "will create a new heart in His people.",
      "prefers steadfast love to sacrifice.",
    ],
    answer: "prefers steadfast love to sacrifice.",
  },
  {
    question: "The call of Gideon was unique because _____",
    options: [
      "he asked for a sign to prove God’s presence.",
      "he fled from the Lord’s angel.",
      "the angel gave him a rod.",
      "the LORD’s angel rejected his sacrifice.",
    ],
    answer: "he asked for a sign to prove God’s presence.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…How long will you go limping with two different opinions?” In this statement, Elijah was asking the Israelites to _____",
    options: [
      "return to the LORD and leave their idols.",
      "bring all their sacrifices to the LORD.",
      "forsake their priests and listen to the LORD.",
      "stop worshipping their gods and live righteously.",
    ],
    answer: "return to the LORD and leave their idols.",
  },
  {
    question: "The Pharisees were offended with Jesus when he _____",
    options: [
      "healed the leper.",
      "healed on the Sabbath.",
      "called himself the Son of Man.",
      "forgave the paralytic.",
    ],
    answer: "healed on the Sabbath.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jesus said, 'Let the children come to me, do not hinder them,' because _____",
    options: [
      "the children needed his blessing.",
      "the disciples were stopping them.",
      "the kingdom of God belongs to such as these.",
      "they were following him.",
    ],
    answer: "the kingdom of God belongs to such as these.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jesus told Peter, 'Before the cock crows, you will deny me three times,' to indicate _____",
    options: [
      "Peter’s future rejection of Jesus.",
      "the loyalty of his disciples.",
      "the strength of his faith.",
      "the kindness of his friends.",
    ],
    answer: "Peter’s future rejection of Jesus.",
  },
  {
    question: "To whom did Jesus say, 'Get behind me, Satan!'?",
    options: ["Peter", "Judas", "James", "John"],
    answer: "Peter",
  },
  {
    question: "The brothers of Joseph were jealous of him because _____",
    options: [
      "their father loved him more.",
      "he was the youngest.",
      "he had a coat of many colors.",
      "he told them about his dreams.",
    ],
    answer: "he told them about his dreams.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the parable of the Good Samaritan, the one who helped the wounded man was a _____",
    options: ["Samaritan", "Pharisee", "Levite", "Priest"],
    answer: "Samaritan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the parable of the lost sheep, Jesus emphasized the joy in heaven over one sinner who _____",
    options: [
      "returns.",
      "receives the word.",
      "repents.",
      "seeks forgiveness.",
    ],
    answer: "repents.",
  },
  {
    question: "During the transfiguration, Jesus’ face shone like the _____",
    options: ["sun.", "stars.", "moon.", "sky."],
    answer: "sun.",
  },
  {
    question: "The role of John the Baptist was to _____",
    options: [
      "prepare the way for the Lord.",
      "gather disciples.",
      "perform miracles.",
      "baptize people in Jordan.",
    ],
    answer: "prepare the way for the Lord.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Paul describes himself as the least of the apostles because _____",
    options: [
      "he was a persecutor of the church.",
      "he was last to be called.",
      "he did not see Jesus in person.",
      "he only preached to Gentiles.",
    ],
    answer: "he was a persecutor of the church.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The person who witnessed the baptism of the Ethiopian eunuch was _____",
    options: ["Philip.", "Peter.", "Paul.", "Stephen."],
    answer: "Philip.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The disciple who brought the boy with five loaves and two fish to Jesus was _____",
    options: ["Andrew.", "Peter.", "Philip.", "James."],
    answer: "Andrew.",
  },
  {
    question: "According to Paul, the fruit of the Spirit includes _____",
    options: [
      "joy, peace, patience, and self-control.",
      "healing and teaching.",
      "strength, courage, and power.",
      "wisdom, knowledge, and discernment.",
    ],
    answer: "joy, peace, patience, and self-control.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When David had the chance to kill Saul, he spared his life because _____",
    options: [
      "Saul was the LORD's anointed.",
      "he feared Saul’s retaliation.",
      "Saul was his relative.",
      "he wanted Saul’s forgiveness.",
    ],
    answer: "Saul was the LORD's anointed.",
  },
  {
    question: "The people of Israel went into exile because they _____",
    options: [
      "worshipped idols and disobeyed God.",
      "killed their prophets.",
      "sought the help of foreign gods.",
      "angered the priests.",
    ],
    answer: "worshipped idols and disobeyed God.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Moses lifted up a bronze serpent in the wilderness so that those who were bitten by snakes could _____",
    options: [
      "look at it and live.",
      "use it as protection.",
      "pray to God.",
      "be healed instantly.",
    ],
    answer: "look at it and live.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The young Samuel first heard the LORD's voice when he was lying down in the _____",
    options: ["temple.", "tabernacle.", "wilderness.", "fields."],
    answer: "temple.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When Elisha told Naaman to wash seven times in the Jordan River, Naaman was _____",
    options: ["angry.", "grateful.", "surprised.", "overjoyed."],
    answer: "angry.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After Jesus healed ten lepers, the only one who returned to thank him was a _____",
    options: ["Samaritan.", "Pharisee.", "Jew.", "priest."],
    answer: "Samaritan.",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On the Day of Pentecost, the disciples were filled with the Holy Spirit and began to speak _____",
    options: [
      "in other languages.",
      "to large crowds.",
      "with new tongues.",
      "about their experiences.",
    ],
    answer: "in other languages.",
  },
  {
    question: "Jesus said, 'I am the good shepherd,' because he _____",
    options: [
      "lays down his life for the sheep.",
      "calls each sheep by name.",
      "knows where to find food for them.",
      "teaches them the right path.",
    ],
    answer: "lays down his life for the sheep.",
  },
  {
    question: "To whom did Jesus say, 'You must be born again'?",
    options: ["Nicodemus.", "Peter.", "Andrew.", "James."],
    answer: "Nicodemus.",
  },
  {
    question: "The one who anointed David as king of Israel was _____",
    options: ["Samuel.", "Saul.", "Nathan.", "Eli."],
    answer: "Samuel.",
  },
  {
    question: "What did Saul do after his defeat of the Amalekites?",
    options: [
      "He set up a monument for himself",
      "He returned to Shiloh",
      "He offered sacrifices to God",
      "He repented of his sins",
    ],
    answer: "He set up a monument for himself",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Let us flee from before Israel: for the Lord fights for them…” The statement above was made by the Egyptian when ____",
    options: [
      "Moses stretched out his hand over the sea",
      "their chariots were clogged in the sea",
      "the LORD drove the sea back by a strong east wind",
      "the angel of God stood between them and Hebrews",
    ],
    answer: "their chariots were clogged in the sea",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Moses told the Israelites that the LORD would give them flesh in the evening and bread in the morning because he had _____",
    options: [
      "heard their prayers",
      "seen their suffering",
      "promised to feed them",
      "heard their murmuring",
    ],
    answer: "heard their murmuring",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Is not David hiding himself on the hill of Hachilah; which is on the east of Jeshimon?” The report above was made to King Saul by the _____",
    options: ["Amalekites", "Philistines", "Hittites", "Ziphites"],
    answer: "Ziphites",
  },
  {
    question:
      "‘The LORD give you children by this woman.' Eli offered this prayer because of Hannah’s _____",
    options: [
      "love for the service",
      "loan of Samuel to the Lord",
      "desire for more children from God",
      "faith in God",
    ],
    answer: "loan of Samuel to the Lord",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The river that flowed out of Eden to water the garden divided and became four rivers namely _____",
    options: [
      "Nile, Pishon, Euphrates, and Tigris",
      "Pishon, Tigris, Gihon, and Nile",
      "Gihon, Pishon, Tigris, and Euphrates",
      "Pishon, Euphrates, Gihon, and Jordan",
    ],
    answer: "Gihon, Pishon, Tigris, and Euphrates",
  },
  {
    question:
      "King Rehoboam refused to take the counsel of the elders because _____",
    options: [
      "it was wrong counsel",
      "he was afraid of the outcome of their counsel",
      "he was stubborn",
      "it was a turn of affairs brought about by the LORD",
    ],
    answer: "it was a turn of affairs brought about by the LORD",
  },
  {
    question:
      "King Saul asked Jesse to send David to him because he wanted David to _____",
    options: [
      "kill Goliath",
      "marry his daughter, Michael",
      "become Jonathan’s friend",
      "serve him",
    ],
    answer: "serve him",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The new covenant God made with the house of Israel and the house of Judah was written on _____",
    options: ["their hearts", "stones", "their foreheads", "tablets"],
    answer: "their hearts",
  },
  {
    question:
      "All the words which the LORD has spoken we will do. What was Moses' response to this declaration by the Israelites?",
    options: [
      "He asked them to pick twelve stones to represent the tribes",
      "He offered peace offerings to the LORD",
      "He charged them to walk faithfully before the LORD",
      "He said that the LORD was witness to their declaration",
    ],
    answer: "He offered peace offerings to the LORD",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The sign of the covenant between God and Noah for all future generations was _____",
    options: ["blood", "treaty of peace", "circumcision", "bow in the cloud"],
    answer: "bow in the cloud",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The signs that God showed to Moses at his call were meant to _____",
    options: [
      "convince the people that he had been sent by God",
      "portray him as superior to the Egyptian magicians",
      "enable him to perform miracles before Pharaoh",
      "convince Pharaoh that he was the prophet of God",
    ],
    answer: "convince the people that he had been sent by God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "King Josiah defiled Topheth, which was in the valley of the sons of Hinnom during his reform in Israel so that _____",
    options: [
      "he might revive the worship of the sun God",
      "he might pull down Topheth and break Molech into pieces",
      "no one would worship Molech",
      "no one might sacrifice human beings again to Molech",
    ],
    answer: "no one might sacrifice human beings again to Molech",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Amos declared that the Jews who built houses of Hewn stone would not dwell in them because they _____",
    options: [
      "trampled upon the poor",
      "persecuted the prophets",
      "swore falsely",
      "worshipped other gods",
    ],
    answer: "trampled upon the poor",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What acts of righteousness did Isaiah admonish his people to demonstrate?",
    options: [
      "helping the poor and offering sacrifice",
      "defending the orphans and respecting the widows",
      "avoiding evils and praying for others",
      "learning to do good and seeking justice",
    ],
    answer: "defending the orphans and respecting the widows",
  },
  {
    question:
      "God promised the faithless Israelites that if they repented of their sins and returned to Him, He would _____",
    options: [
      "deliver their enemies into their hands",
      "fill them with His knowledge",
      "give them favor in the sight of the nations",
      "give them shepherds after His own heart",
    ],
    answer: "give them shepherds after His own heart",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“...When my soul fainted within me, I remembered the LORD; and my prayer came to thee…” The prayer above was offered by Jonah _____",
    options: [
      "at Nineveh",
      "at Tarshish",
      "in the ship",
      "in the belly of the fish",
    ],
    answer: "in the belly of the fish",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“The ark of the God of Israel must not remain with us...” The Philistines who made the statement above were anxious to get rid of the ark because _____",
    options: [
      "they could not handle it",
      "the hand of God was heavy upon them",
      "their women were becoming barren",
      "the Israelites had mustered forces against them",
    ],
    answer: "the hand of God was heavy upon them",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“At the time shall arise.... the great prince who has charge of your people...” In the statement above by Daniel, the great prince refers to _____",
    options: ["Gabriel", "the Deliverer", "Michael", "the Messiah"],
    answer: "Michael",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Hosea, the LORD would not have pity upon the children of his faithless wife because _____",
    options: [
      "they were rebellious children",
      "they had not been faithful",
      "their mother had not shown pity on them",
      "their mother had played the harlot",
    ],
    answer: "their mother had played the harlot",
  },
  {
    question:
      "God decided not to bring evil in Ahab’s days but in the days of his son because Ahab _____",
    options: [
      "asked God for mercy",
      "returned Naboth’s vineyard",
      "fasted for forty days",
      "humbled himself before God",
    ],
    answer: "humbled himself before God",
  },
  {
    question: "When the Babylonians captured King Zedekiah, they _____",
    options: [
      "killed him immediately",
      "assaulted his wives in his presence",
      "put out his eyes",
      "took his sons to Babylon",
    ],
    answer: "put out his eyes",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The men who threw Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego into the fire were _____",
    options: [
      "amazed that the Hebrews were not burnt",
      "assisted to escape from being burnt",
      "promoted by the king",
      "consumed by the flames",
    ],
    answer: "consumed by the flames",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Hear this word, you cows of Bashan... who oppress the poor, who crush the needy...” Cows of Bashan in the statement above refers to the _____",
    options: [
      "wicked kings",
      "women of Samaria",
      "Judges in Israel",
      "false prophets",
    ],
    answer: "women of Samaria",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“It is enough; now O LORD, take away my life; for I am no better than my fathers.” The prayer above was said by Elijah when _____",
    options: [
      "he ran out of food",
      "he had no water to drink at the brook Cherith",
      "he learned that Ahab was looking for him",
      "he was threatened by Jezebel",
    ],
    answer: "he was threatened by Jezebel",
  },
  {
    question: "In his prayer of penitence, David requested God to _____",
    options: [
      "punish his enemies",
      "avenge his son’s death",
      "cast him not away from His presence",
      "deliver him from idolatry",
    ],
    answer: "cast him not away from His presence",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When Moses requested the Israelites to donate materials for the construction of the Tabernacle, the people responded by _____",
    options: [
      "giving only silver and bronze",
      "offering more than was needed",
      "donating just a few materials",
      "giving only the resources they had",
    ],
    answer: "offering more than was needed",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When Saul said ‘Cursed be the man who eats food until it is evening and I am avenged on my enemies,’ he was making the people to _____",
    options: [
      "focus on killing their enemies",
      "honor him for killing their enemies",
      "take an oath of allegiance to him",
      "defend his kingship",
    ],
    answer: "focus on killing their enemies",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When Joseph’s brethren saw that their father loved him more than all his brethren, they _____",
    options: [
      "conspired against him",
      "were sorry for him",
      "resented him",
      "fled from him",
    ],
    answer: "resented him",
  },
  {
    question: "According to Hosea, the knowledge of God is more than _____",
    options: [
      "sin offerings",
      "burnt offerings",
      "peace offerings",
      "thank offerings",
    ],
    answer: "burnt offerings",
  },
  {
    question: "Eli was unable to control his two sons because _____",
    options: [
      "they were too powerful for him",
      "he feared for his life",
      "they had no regard for God",
      "he loved them too much",
    ],
    answer: "they had no regard for God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“And the LORD said unto Joshua, See I have given into thy hand Jericho...” The statement above indicates that _____",
    options: [
      "the battle was already won",
      "the children of Israel were fearful",
      "the Israelites would wage war",
      "God’s plan would unfold gradually",
    ],
    answer: "the battle was already won",
  },
  {
    question:
      "During the last plague in Egypt, the blood of the lamb was to be a _____",
    options: [
      "mark of God's favor on Israel",
      "symbol of Pharaoh’s defeat",
      "reminder of Moses’ power",
      "sign for the people to remember",
    ],
    answer: "mark of God's favor on Israel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the book of Job, who was the first to speak after Job was struck by disaster?",
    options: ["Job’s wife", "Eliphaz", "Bildad", "Elihu"],
    answer: "Job’s wife",
  },
  {
    question: "David was able to withstand Goliath because _____",
    options: [
      "he had superior weaponry",
      "he trusted in the LORD",
      "he had the support of the king",
      "he was well-prepared physically",
    ],
    answer: "he trusted in the LORD",
  },
  {
    question: "The Ten Commandments were given to the Israelites at _____",
    options: ["Mount Horeb", "Mount Sinai", "Bethlehem", "the Red Sea"],
    answer: "Mount Sinai",
  },
  {
    question: "According to Jesus, the eye is the _____ of the body.",
    options: ["window", "light", "reflection", "measure"],
    answer: "light",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the parable of the sower, the seed that fell on good soil represents those who _____",
    options: [
      "hear the word and understand it",
      "hear the word and accept it",
      "hear the word but do not act",
      "hear the word and bear no fruit",
    ],
    answer: "hear the word and understand it",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Paul, Christians should _____ to ensure that love remains without hypocrisy.",
    options: [
      "abhor what is evil",
      "pray for the needy",
      "fast regularly",
      "offer thanks",
    ],
    answer: "abhor what is evil",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the king that decreed that all his kingdom should fast in response to Jonah’s preaching?",
    options: ["Nebuchadnezzar", "David", "Ahab", "The King of Nineveh"],
    answer: "The King of Nineveh",
  },
  {
    question: "The woman with the issue of blood was healed because she _____",
    options: ["followed Jesus", "prayed", "believed", "touched His garment"],
    answer: "touched His garment",
  },
  {
    question: "When Jesus healed a paralytic, he was accused of _____",
    options: [
      "performing a false miracle",
      "blasphemy",
      "disobeying Moses",
      "performing a trick",
    ],
    answer: "blasphemy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "At the pool of Bethesda, Jesus healed the man who had been sick for _____",
    options: ["12 years", "18 years", "38 years", "25 years"],
    answer: "38 years",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Paul taught that believers who live according to the Spirit are _____",
    options: ["sons of Abraham", "sons of God", "perfect", "wise"],
    answer: "sons of God",
  },
  {
    question: "The apostle Paul was born in _____",
    options: ["Tarsus", "Bethlehem", "Nazareth", "Jerusalem"],
    answer: "Tarsus",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jesus taught that those who hunger and thirst for righteousness will _____",
    options: ["be filled", "receive mercy", "see God", "inherit the earth"],
    answer: "be filled",
  },
  {
    question: "The shortest verse in the Bible is _____",
    options: ["Jesus wept", "God is love", "Rejoice evermore", "Fear not"],
    answer: "Jesus wept",
  },
  {
    question: "Which fruit of the Spirit did Paul say is the greatest?",
    options: ["Joy", "Faith", "Hope", "Love"],
    answer: "Love",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The parable of the Good Samaritan was told by Jesus to illustrate _____",
    options: ["hospitality", "faithfulness", "true love", "neighborliness"],
    answer: "neighborliness",
  },
  {
    question: "David did not allow Abishai to destroy Saul because he _____",
    options: [
      "believed in the judgement of God",
      "wanted to avoid being guilty before the Lord",
      "wanted to disarm Saul before killing him",
      "wanted to see if Saul would repent eventually",
    ],
    answer: "wanted to avoid being guilty before the Lord",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The reward for total obedience to the commandments of God is _____",
    options: [
      "wisdom",
      "life and length of days",
      "knowledge",
      "marital possessions",
    ],
    answer: "life and length of days",
  },
  {
    question: "Adam named his wife Eve because she was _____",
    options: [
      "deceived by the serpent",
      "the one that misled him",
      "the bone of his bones",
      "the mother of all living",
    ],
    answer: "the mother of all living",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the immediate reaction of Moses when he cast his rod on the ground at Mount Hereb and it became a serpent?",
    options: [
      "He shouted for joy",
      "He fled from it",
      "He took it by the tail",
      "He caught it immediately",
    ],
    answer: "He fled from it",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The consequence of King Solomon’s failure to keep the LORD’s commandment was _____",
    options: [
      "God’s promise to tear away part of the kingdom",
      "the disloyalty of his subjects",
      "the rebellion of the vassal states against his rule",
      "the loss of God’s favour",
    ],
    answer: "God’s promise to tear away part of the kingdom",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Prophet Isaiah, the creative ability of God is likened to that of a _____",
    options: [
      "potter and his earthen vessel",
      "ruler and his followers",
      "master and his servant",
      "shepherd and his sheep",
    ],
    answer: "potter and his earthen vessel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“David departed from there and escaped... and when his brothers and all his father’s house heard it...” In the statement above, where did David escape to?",
    options: [
      "Mizpeh of Moab",
      "The land of Judah",
      "The cave of Abdullam",
      "The wilderness of Engedi",
    ],
    answer: "The cave of Abdullam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Hiram, King of Tyre, was friendly with King Solomon because he _____",
    options: [
      "was afraid of war",
      "wanted to assist",
      "loved the wisdom of Solomon",
      "loved David, Solomon’s father",
    ],
    answer: "loved the wisdom of Solomon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Go from your country and your kindred and your father’s house to the land that I will show you...” Where was Abraham when this command was given?",
    options: ["Sheckem", "Bethel", "Ur", "Haran"],
    answer: "Ur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The LORD repented of the evil which he intended for His people because Moses _____",
    options: [
      "burnt the golden calf which the people made",
      "broke the tablets out of his hands",
      "made the people drink of the water of the burnt calf",
      "reminded Him of his promise to Abraham, Isaac and Israel",
    ],
    answer: "reminded Him of his promise to Abraham, Isaac and Israel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The altar that Gideon built at the oak of Ophrah was called _____",
    options: [
      "The LORD is present",
      "The LORD is strength",
      "The LORD is peace",
      "The LORD is great",
    ],
    answer: "The LORD is peace",
  },
  {
    question: "Moses sent men to spy out the land of Canaan in order to _____",
    options: [
      "measure the entire land",
      "share out the land",
      "know if it was good or bad",
      "know if it was flowing with milk and honey",
    ],
    answer: "know if it was flowing with milk and honey",
  },
  {
    question: "The second creation story ends with the institution of _____",
    options: ["the sabbath", "the Passover", "marriage", "circumcision"],
    answer: "marriage",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The greatest domestic problem King David experienced which almost cost him his kingdom was _____",
    options: [
      "his adultery with Bathsheba",
      "the killing of Uriah",
      "the proclamation of Adonijah asking",
      "the revolt of Absalom against him",
    ],
    answer: "the revolt of Absalom against him",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The declaration by God that he would make a nation of the son of the slave woman meant that He _____",
    options: [
      "recognized Ishmael as Abraham’s descendant",
      "was not partial towards Isaac and Ishmael",
      "did not like the way Ishmael was sent out by Abraham",
      "was responsible for sending Ishmael out of Abraham’s house",
    ],
    answer: "recognized Ishmael as Abraham’s descendant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The chief butler said to Pharaoh, “I remember my faults today...” Faults refer to his _____",
    options: [
      "sins before he was imprisoned by Pharaoh",
      "inability to interpret Pharaoh’s dream",
      "inability to identify competent magicians, wise men and interpreters of dreams",
      "forgetting the young Hebrew who interpreted his dream correctly while in prison",
    ],
    answer:
      "forgetting the young Hebrew who interpreted his dream correctly while in prison",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“...The earth produced of itself, first the blade, then the ear, then the full grain in the ear...” The statement above was made by Jesus in the parable of the _____",
    options: ["sower", "mustard seed", "weeds", "seed growing secretly"],
    answer: "seed growing secretly",
  },
  {
    question: "Peter became frightened as he walked on the sea because _____",
    options: [
      "he saw a ghost",
      "he doubted Jesus",
      "of the wind",
      "it was dark and cloudy",
    ],
    answer: "of the wind",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What did the blind man by the roadside near Jericho do on receiving his sight?",
    options: [
      "he jumped for joy and went away",
      "he thanked Jesus for healing him",
      "He followed Jesus, glorifying God",
      "he gave praise to God for making him whole",
    ],
    answer: "He followed Jesus, glorifying God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The order of the crucifixion events according to Luke’s Gospel is _____",
    options: [
      "crucifixion, lots casting for His dress, scoffing and mockery",
      "mockery, lots casting for His dress, scoffing and crucifixion",
      "lots casting for His dress, mockery, scoffing and crucifixion",
      "crucifixion, scoffing, mockery and lots casting for His dress",
    ],
    answer: "crucifixion, lots casting for His dress, scoffing and mockery",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The angel told Zachariah that John the Baptist would drink no wine nor strong drink because he would _____",
    options: [
      "be the forerunner of Jesus",
      "only eat locusts and wild honey",
      "be filled with the Holy Spirit",
      "baptize sinners who would come to him",
    ],
    answer: "be filled with the Holy Spirit",
  },
  {
    question: "What were the two emblems Jesus used during the Last Supper?",
    options: [
      "the bread and the blood of the lamb",
      "the bread and the wine",
      "The unleavened bread and the fruit of the vine",
      "his blood and his body",
    ],
    answer: "the bread and the wine",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The condition Peter gave for a person that would replace Judas Iscariot was that he must be _____",
    options: [
      "a witness to Jesus ministry",
      "full of faith",
      "a disciple of John the Baptist",
      "a Galilean",
    ],
    answer: "a witness to Jesus ministry",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“They have no wine” Jesus immediate response to the statement above was _____",
    options: [
      "“Do whatever he tells you”",
      "“Fill the jar with water”",
      "“...Draw some out and take it to the steward of the feast”",
      "“O woman, what does this have to do with me?”",
    ],
    answer: "“O woman, what does this have to do with me?”",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The statement of Jesus that he came to seek and save that which was lost indicates that _____",
    options: [
      "he loved the world",
      "he forgives sins",
      "he came to call sinners",
      "he gives life abundantly",
    ],
    answer: "he came to call sinners",
  },
  {
    question: "The first miracle of Jesus was _____",
    options: [
      "the resurrection of Lazarus",
      "the healing of a leper",
      "changing water into wine",
      "the healing of the blind man",
    ],
    answer: "changing water into wine",
  },
  {
    question: "The man who sought to worship the Lord in vain was _____",
    options: [
      "the rich young ruler",
      "the scribes and Pharisees",
      "Simon the sorcerer",
      "the publicans",
    ],
    answer: "the scribes and Pharisees",
  },
  {
    question: "The punishment of Herod for refusing to honour God was _____",
    options: [
      "he was struck blind",
      "he was bitten by a snake",
      "he was eaten by worms",
      "he fell down dead",
    ],
    answer: "he was eaten by worms",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The proclamation by John the Baptist of the coming of the Messiah was _____",
    options: [
      "the great news of salvation",
      "the witness of the light",
      "the good news of the Kingdom",
      "the revelation of God’s mercy",
    ],
    answer: "the good news of the Kingdom",
  },
  {
    question: "The early church devoted themselves to the _____",
    options: [
      "fellowship and prayers",
      "breaking of bread and prayers",
      "study of the scriptures and prayers",
      "preaching of the word and prayers",
    ],
    answer: "breaking of bread and prayers",
  },
  {
    question: "Peter addressed his sermon on the Day of Pentecost to _____",
    options: [
      "the chief priests",
      "the Romans",
      "the twelve apostles",
      "the people of Israel",
    ],
    answer: "the people of Israel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The statement that Paul made, ‘I have fought the good fight’ indicates that _____",
    options: [
      "he was tired of fighting",
      "he had won the race",
      "he was aware of his calling",
      "he had kept the faith",
    ],
    answer: "he had kept the faith",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The duration of time God took to create the earth is recorded in _____",
    options: [
      "the book of Genesis",
      "the book of Numbers",
      "the book of Deuteronomy",
      "the book of Exodus",
    ],
    answer: "the book of Genesis",
  },
  {
    question: "The call to Abraham was to take him from _____",
    options: [
      "Haran to Canaan",
      "Ur to Canaan",
      "Haran to Egypt",
      "Egypt to Canaan",
    ],
    answer: "Ur to Canaan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is not a name for Jesus?",
    options: [
      "Alpha and Omega",
      "The Lamb of God",
      "The Lion of Judah",
      "The Star of David",
    ],
    answer: "The Star of David",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When the Lord first appeared to Samuel, the child of Hannah, He was _____",
    options: [
      "speaking in a dream",
      "in a vision",
      "in a dream while he slept",
      "in a vision while he prayed",
    ],
    answer: "in a dream while he slept",
  },
  {
    question: "The names of Moses’ parents were _____",
    options: [
      "Jochebed and Aaron",
      "Aaron and Miriam",
      "Amram and Jochebed",
      "Phinehas and Jochebed",
    ],
    answer: "Amram and Jochebed",
  },
  {
    question: "The first sin recorded in the Bible was that of _____",
    options: ["murder", "deception", "disobedience", "pride"],
    answer: "disobedience",
  },
  {
    question: "The location of Jesus’ first miracle is _____",
    options: [
      "the house of Jairus",
      "the wedding feast in Cana",
      "Bethlehem",
      "Jerusalem",
    ],
    answer: "the wedding feast in Cana",
  },
  {
    question: "The last book of the New Testament is _____",
    options: ["Revelation", "Jude", "Hebrews", "James"],
    answer: "Revelation",
  },
  {
    question: "The birthplace of Jesus is _____",
    options: ["Jerusalem", "Cana", "Bethlehem", "Nazareth"],
    answer: "Bethlehem",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT a fruit of the Spirit?",
    options: ["patience", "kindness", "humility", "self-control"],
    answer: "humility",
  },
  {
    question: "The first person to see the resurrected Jesus was _____",
    options: ["Mary Magdalene", "Peter", "John", "Thomas"],
    answer: "Mary Magdalene",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the primary function of the mitochondria in eukaryotic cells?",
    options: [
      "To produce energy in the form of ATP",
      "To synthesize proteins",
      "To store genetic information",
      "To detoxify harmful substances",
    ],
    answer: "To produce energy in the form of ATP",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which part of the plant is primarily responsible for photosynthesis?",
    options: ["Roots", "Stems", "Leaves", "Flowers"],
    answer: "Leaves",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the basic unit of life?",
    options: ["Atom", "Molecule", "Cell", "Tissue"],
    answer: "Cell",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What type of bond holds the two strands of a DNA molecule together?",
    options: ["Ionic bond", "Covalent bond", "Hydrogen bond", "Peptide bond"],
    answer: "Hydrogen bond",
  },
  {
    question: "Which organelle is known as the 'powerhouse of the cell'?",
    options: [
      "Ribosome",
      "Endoplasmic reticulum",
      "Golgi apparatus",
      "Mitochondria",
    ],
    answer: "Mitochondria",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the primary role of chlorophyll in plants?",
    options: [
      "Absorbing sunlight for photosynthesis",
      "Transporting water",
      "Storing energy",
      "Regulating gas exchange",
    ],
    answer: "Absorbing sunlight for photosynthesis",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which process do plants use to convert light energy into chemical energy?",
    options: ["Respiration", "Photosynthesis", "Transpiration", "Fermentation"],
    answer: "Photosynthesis",
  },
  {
    question: "Moses sent men to spy out the land of Canaan in order to _____",
    options: [
      "measure the entire land",
      "share out the land",
      "know if it was good or bad",
      "know if it was flowing with milk and honey",
    ],
    answer: "know if it was flowing with milk and honey",
  },
  {
    question: "The two sons of Samuel that became Judges in Israel were _____",
    options: [
      "Joel and Abidjah",
      "Abimelech and Abidjah",
      "Hophni and Phinehas",
      "Joel and Abimelech",
    ],
    answer: "Hophni and Phinehas",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Let us make man in our image, after our likeness...” In the statement above, in our image implies man _____",
    options: [
      "becoming God",
      "being a representative of God and fellowmen",
      "being like God",
      "becoming the exact picture of God",
    ],
    answer: "being like God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The murmuring of the congregation in the wilderness against Moses and Aaron were an indication of the people’s _____",
    options: [
      "lack of patience with them",
      "lack of faith in them",
      "fear of dying by the sword",
      "inability to get to the promise land",
    ],
    answer: "lack of faith in them",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When the glory of the LORD appeared to Moses and Aaron in the wilderness of Zin, the Lord said they should _____",
    options: [
      "tell the rock before their eyes to yield its water",
      "strike the rock with rod to bring out water for them",
      "fetch water for the people and their cattle",
      "tell the people to go around the rock",
    ],
    answer: "tell the rock before their eyes to yield its water",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The last event that boosted Gideon’s courage to go against the Midianites was the _____",
    options: [
      "appearance of the angel who called him a man of valour",
      "sign in which God caused the dew to be on the fleece",
      "test God gave Gideon’s men at the waterside",
      "dream told by the Midianites about the barley bread",
    ],
    answer: "dream told by the Midianites about the barley bread",
  },
  {
    question:
      "At the confirmation of the covenant, after Moses had addressed the people, they answered and said, _____",
    options: [
      "We are going to obey the Lord our God",
      "to beware of false prophets and teachers",
      "obeying fully the Ten Commandments",
      "We shall keep all the Commandments of God",
    ],
    answer: "We shall keep all the Commandments of God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Saul visited the witch of Endor when he was besieged by the _____",
    options: ["Philistines", "Amorites", "Amalekites", "Moabites"],
    answer: "Philistines",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Why did Saul tell the Kenites to go away from among the Amalekites?",
    options: [
      "God did not tell him to destroy the Kenites",
      "Saul married from the Kenites",
      "The Kenites showed kindness to Israel",
      "The Kenites had blood covenant with Israel",
    ],
    answer: "The Kenites showed kindness to Israel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“...And they shall be my people, and I will be their God...” This covenant was made with Israel through prophet",
    options: ["Isaiah", "Jeremiah", "Amos", "Hosea"],
    answer: "Jeremiah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many sons of Jesse passed before Samuel before David was chosen as King?",
    options: ["5", "6", "7", "8"],
    answer: "7",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Whoever does not come out after Saul and Samuel, so shall it be done to his oxen!”",
    options: [
      "The power of the Lord came upon them",
      "The dread of the Lord came upon them",
      "The spirit of the Lord came upon them",
      "The word of the Lord came to them",
    ],
    answer: "The spirit of the Lord came upon them",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“...Do not forsake her, and she will keep you, love her and she will guard you...”",
    options: ["intelligence", "wife", "knowledge", "wisdom"],
    answer: "wisdom",
  },
  {
    question: "Joseph was made prime minister in Egypt because he _____",
    options: [
      "interpreted the dreams of Pharaoh’s servants in the prison",
      "resisted the temptation by Potiphar’s wife",
      "was a faithful and upright man",
      "interpreted Pharaoh’s dream and counselled him to what to do",
    ],
    answer: "interpreted Pharaoh’s dream and counselled him to what to do",
  },
  {
    question: "Nehemiah in exile functioned as the King’s _____",
    options: ["guard", "secretary", "cupbearer", "adviser"],
    answer: "cupbearer",
  },
  {
    question: "In days of Uzziah, Isaiah saw a vision concerning _____",
    options: [
      "Samaria and Judah",
      "Judah and Jerusalem",
      "Samaria and Jerusalem",
      "Judah and Israel",
    ],
    answer: "Judah and Israel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "God said that any member of Ahab’s family who died in the open country would be _____",
    options: [
      "eaten up by the dogs",
      "buried by foreigners",
      "eaten by the birds",
      "left unburied",
    ],
    answer: "eaten up by the dogs",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“Take away all iniquity; accept that which is good...” What was the iniquity Hosea was referring to in the statement above?",
    options: ["Adultery", "Ignorance", "Idolatry", "Injustice"],
    answer: "Idolatry",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Jeremiah, the role of the shepherds which God will give to His people is to _____",
    options: [
      "feed the people with knowledge and understanding",
      "heal the guilt of the people",
      "gather the scattered children of Israel",
      "lead them to greener pastures",
    ],
    answer: "feed the people with knowledge and understanding",
  },
  {
    question:
      "King Nebuchadnezzar assembled the straps, the prefects and the governors to _____",
    options: [
      "tell him his dream",
      "send them to the provinces",
      "interpret his dream",
      "the dedication of the image",
    ],
    answer: "interpret his dream",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did Elijah kill all the prophets of Baal after the contest with Ahab?",
    options: ["Kishon", "Carmel", "Zaraphath", "Cherith"],
    answer: "Kishon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“...The fathers have eaten sour grapes, and the children’s teeth are set on edge...”",
    options: [
      "parents are punished for the sins of their children",
      "children are punished for the sins of their parents",
      "parents are punished for the sins of their grandparents",
      "great grandchildren are punished for the sins of their forefathers",
    ],
    answer: "children are punished for the sins of their parents",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After Jonah had been thrown into the sea and the sea ceased from its raging, the men with him _____",
    options: [
      "praised the Lord for saving them",
      "feared the LORD, offered sacrifice and made vows",
      "prayed to God for forgiveness",
      "rowed hard to bring the ship back to land",
    ],
    answer: "feared the LORD, offered sacrifice and made vows",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Zedekiah, the king of Judah, was captured by the army of the Chaldeans _____",
    options: [
      "at Riblah",
      "in the plains of Jericho",
      "at Arabah",
      "on the outskirts of Jerusalem",
    ],
    answer: "at Riblah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Two Christian virtues to be learned in the story of the good Samaritan are _____",
    options: [
      "kindness and fairness",
      "justice and humility",
      "compassion and humility",
      "compassion and mercy",
    ],
    answer: "compassion and mercy",
  },
  {
    question: "How did Jesus prove that he had power over death?",
    options: [
      "By raising the dead",
      "By healing the sick",
      "By cleansing the leper",
      "By preaching to the poor",
    ],
    answer: "By raising the dead",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following statements is true about man in the image of God?",
    options: [
      "Man is different from animals",
      "Man is a rational being",
      "Man is a moral being",
      "All of the above",
    ],
    answer: "All of the above",
  },
  {
    question: "In the Bible, the Old Testament was given to Israel _____",
    options: [
      "to keep them safe",
      "to teach them to be holy",
      "to bless them",
      "to guide them",
    ],
    answer: "to teach them to be holy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The part of the Old Testament where God expressed His will through the prophetic writings is known as _____",
    options: [
      "the law",
      "the wisdom literature",
      "the history books",
      "the prophetic books",
    ],
    answer: "the prophetic books",
  },
  {
    question: "Paul said that the last enemy that shall be destroyed is _____",
    options: ["fear", "Satan", "death", "disease"],
    answer: "death",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Paul in Romans 12:2, we are to renew our minds so that we can _____",
    options: [
      "know the will of God",
      "be transformed",
      "become holy",
      "be righteous",
    ],
    answer: "know the will of God",
  },
  {
    question: "The book of Revelation is divided into _____",
    options: ["6 parts", "4 sections", "3 sections", "5 sections"],
    answer: "3 sections",
  },
  {
    question: "The book of Daniel portrays a God who _____",
    options: ["saves His people", "is sovereign", "is faithful", "is merciful"],
    answer: "is sovereign",
  },
  {
    question: "At the beginning of his ministry, Jesus quoted _____",
    options: ["Isaiah", "the psalms", "Malachi", "Genesis"],
    answer: "Isaiah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In the Gospel of John, Jesus said to the Samaritan woman at the well, “If you knew the gift of God and who it is that says to you, ‘Give me a drink,’ you would have asked him, and he would have given you _____",
    options: ["living water", "eternal life", "abundant grace", "healing"],
    answer: "living water",
  },
  {
    question: "The parable of the sower emphasizes _____",
    options: [
      "the condition of the heart",
      "the power of the word",
      "the need for perseverance",
      "the importance of faith",
    ],
    answer: "the condition of the heart",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The woman at the well was surprised that Jesus spoke to her because _____",
    options: [
      "she was a Samaritan",
      "she was a sinner",
      "she was a Gentile",
      "she was an outcast",
    ],
    answer: "she was a Samaritan",
  },
  {
    question: "The account of the resurrection of Jesus is found in _____",
    options: [
      "Matthew, Mark, Luke, John",
      "Matthew, Luke, John",
      "Mark and John",
      "Matthew and Mark",
    ],
    answer: "Matthew, Mark, Luke, John",
  },
  {
    question: "The teaching of the apostles is often referred to as _____",
    options: [
      "the doctrine of the church",
      "the traditions of men",
      "the teachings of Christ",
      "the foundational truths",
    ],
    answer: "the doctrine of the church",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The gift of the Holy Spirit was first given to believers on _____",
    options: [
      "the day of Pentecost",
      "the day of atonement",
      "the feast of trumpets",
      "the feast of tabernacles",
    ],
    answer: "the day of Pentecost",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jesus told Peter to cast his nets into the deep for a catch after _____",
    options: [
      "fishing all night",
      "hearing Jesus preach",
      "the storm calmed down",
      "he was chosen as a disciple",
    ],
    answer: "fishing all night",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What effect did the sudden death of Ananias and Sapphira have on the early disciples?",
    options: [
      "Many more disciples were won to God",
      "Great fear gripped them all",
      "The disciples became more united",
      "Apostle Peter was highly respected",
    ],
    answer: "Great fear gripped them all",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Paul and Barnabas were sent out on the first missionary work from Antioch to Seleucia by the _____",
    options: [
      "prophets and teachers",
      "church elders",
      "other disciples",
      "Holy Spirit",
    ],
    answer: "Holy Spirit",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…We must work the works of him who sent me, while it is day; night comes, when no one can work” Jesus made the statement above after the healing of the _____",
    options: [
      "centurion’s servant",
      "ten lepers",
      "man born blind",
      "paralytic man",
    ],
    answer: "man born blind",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“They have taken the Lord out of the tomb, and we do not know where they have laid him.” What happened immediately after Mary Magdalene made the statement above?",
    options: [
      "Peter and the other disciple went towards the tomb",
      "the guards were afraid and ran away from the tomb",
      "Mary stood, weeping outside the tomb",
      "two angels appeared to Mary by the tomb",
    ],
    answer: "Peter and the other disciple went towards the tomb",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…For if this plan or this undertaking is of men, it will fail; but if it is of God, you will not be able to overthrow them…” This Gamaliel’s statement above refers to _____",
    options: [
      "Peter and John",
      "Peter and the apostles",
      "Paul and Timothy",
      "Paul and Silas",
    ],
    answer: "Peter and the apostles",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jesus declared that men love darkness rather than light because _____",
    options: [
      "their hearts were hardened",
      "they had no truth",
      "they had been blinded",
      "their deeds were evil",
    ],
    answer: "their deeds were evil",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…This Jesus God raised up, and of that we all are witnesses…” The statement above was made by Peter on the occasion of his _____",
    options: [
      "sermon on the day of Pentecost",
      "release from prison by the Jews",
      "healing of the lame man at the gate called Beautiful",
      "address to the disciples for the replacement of Judas",
    ],
    answer: "sermon on the day of Pentecost",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to John, he who does not believe in the only Son of God is _____",
    options: [
      "none of his own",
      "not worthy of the Kingdom",
      "cast off as a branch",
      "condemned already",
    ],
    answer: "condemned already",
  },
  {
    question:
      "“…Are you the only visitor to Jerusalem who does not know the things that have happened there in these days?” The things being referred to in the statement above are the _____",
    options: [
      "arrest, trials and judgment of Jesus",
      "crucifixion, death and resurrection of Jesus",
      "triumphal entry and cleansing of the temple",
      "birth and presentation of Jesus",
    ],
    answer: "crucifixion, death and resurrection of Jesus",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Paul, just as the law came to increase trespass, so sin came to increase _____",
    options: ["righteousness", "punishment", "grace", "ungodliness"],
    answer: "grace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Peter, Christians who suffer according to the will of God will receive _____",
    options: [
      "forgiveness",
      "the Crown of Glory",
      "the Holy Spirit",
      "blessing",
    ],
    answer: "the Crown of Glory",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Paul declares that Christians have the same functions, but they have gifts that differ according to _____",
    options: [
      "their devotion of prayer",
      "their suffering and endurance",
      "grace given to them",
      "enablement by the spirit",
    ],
    answer: "grace given to them",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Romans, as one man’s trespass led to condemnation for all, so will one man’s act of righteousness lead to _____",
    options: [
      "acquittal and life for all men",
      "salvation and new life for all men",
      "justification and hope for all men",
      "sanctification and life for all men",
    ],
    answer: "justification and hope for all men",
  },
  {
    question:
      "‘And let steadfastness have its full effect…’ What does James say would be the outcome of this effect?",
    options: [
      "Righteousness and faith.",
      "Trial and endurance",
      "Humanity and obedience",
      "Perfection and completion",
    ],
    answer: "Perfection and completion",
  },
  {
    question:
      "‘Have this mind among yourselves, which is yours in Christ Jesus…’ This mind in Paul’s statement above means a mind of _____",
    options: ["humanity", "faith", "holiness", "prayer"],
    answer: "humanity",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Peter teaches that servants should be submissive to their masters with all respect, not only to the kind and gentle but also to the _____",
    options: ["impatient", "inconsiderate", "wicked", "overbearing"],
    answer: "overbearing",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In Romans, Christians are admonished to put on the Lord Jesus Christ and not to _____",
    options: [
      "rely on the law",
      "judge one another",
      "make provision for the flesh",
      "take advantage of one another",
    ],
    answer: "make provision for the flesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Paul teaches that those who have been baptized into Christ have been baptized into His _____",
    options: ["service", "death", "kingdom", "suffering"],
    answer: "death",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On the third day of their capture of the Ark of God, the Philistines discovered that _____",
    options: [
      "Dagon, their god, had fallen and broken to pieces",
      "Dagon had disappeared from its place",
      "The Ark has swallowed Dagon, their god",
      "The Ark had been standing on Dagon",
    ],
    answer: "Dagon, their god, had fallen and broken to pieces",
  },
  {
    question:
      "One of the sins of Manasseh for which the LORD sent bands of the Chaldeans, Syrians, Moabites and Ammonites to destroy Judah was _____",
    options: [
      "the release of a thousand captives",
      "his failure to obey God’s prophets",
      "the arrest of the King of Babylon",
      "the shedding of innocent blood",
    ],
    answer: "the shedding of innocent blood",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Elijah decreed that there would be neither rain nor dew for three years because _____",
    options: [
      "Ahab had forsaken the commandment of God by erecting an altar for Baal",
      "Nebat the son of Rehoboam connived with Ahab to kill him",
      "he was sure that he would be fed by the ravens",
      "Jezebel the wife of Ahab killed Obadiah",
    ],
    answer:
      "Ahab had forsaken the commandment of God by erecting an altar for Baal",
  },
  {
    question: "God called Jonah and sent him to the people of Nineveh to _____",
    options: [
      "pray for their repentance",
      "pray to Him for their forgiveness",
      "cry against their wickedness",
      "preach His word to them",
    ],
    answer: "cry against their wickedness",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Consequent upon the murder of Naboth by Ahab and Jezebel, God declared that ____",
    options: [
      "dogs would lick Ahab’s blood where they had licked Naboth’s",
      "Ahab’s descendants would never ascend the throne in Israel",
      "He would require the blood of Naboth from Ahab’s hand",
      "the sword would not depart from the house of Ahab",
    ],
    answer: "dogs would lick Ahab’s blood where they had licked Naboth’s",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to Amos, God decided to raise up a nation that would fight and oppress Israel because the people _____",
    options: [
      "were disobedient",
      "worshipped foreign gods",
      "continued to be wicked",
      "had fallen from grace",
    ],
    answer: "continued to be wicked",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The people of Israel went out and plundered the Egyptians as they were leaving Egypt in obedience to the _____",
    options: [
      "word of the Lord",
      "mighty hand of God",
      "command of Moses",
      "dreams of Pharaoh",
    ],
    answer: "word of the Lord",
  },
  {
    question: "Jacob deceived his father Isaac by using _____",
    options: [
      "a garment of Esau",
      "the skin of a goat",
      "the words of Esau",
      "his mother’s scheming",
    ],
    answer: "the skin of a goat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Israelites journeyed from Rephidim to Mt. Sinai because God instructed Moses to go there and meet him so that _____",
    options: [
      "He would show him His glory",
      "He would send Moses to the wilderness",
      "He would give the people the Law",
      "He would show the way to Canaan",
    ],
    answer: "He would give the people the Law",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Daniel interpreted the dream of Nebuchadnezzar about a great statue that represented the ______",
    options: [
      "kingdom of Babylon",
      "universal kingdoms",
      "pride of nations",
      "human desires",
    ],
    answer: "universal kingdoms",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Moses was prevented from entering the promised land because of _____",
    options: [
      "his rebellion against God",
      "his anger at the Israelites",
      "his disobedience to God",
      "his murder of an Egyptian",
    ],
    answer: "his disobedience to God",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When Solomon became king, he requested that God should give him _____",
    options: ["wealth", "power and strength", "wisdom", "long life"],
    answer: "wisdom",
  },
  {
    question:
      "This person deceived the King of Israel by pretending to be an injured man. Who is he?",
    options: ["Jehu", "Ahab", "Zedekiah", "Micaiah"],
    answer: "Zedekiah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The person who threw himself on the ground to worship David and to declare him king was _____",
    options: ["Abner", "Nathan", "Joab", "Zadok"],
    answer: "Zadok",
  },
  {
    question: "The first king of Israel was _____",
    options: ["Saul", "David", "Solomon", "Absalom"],
    answer: "Saul",
  },
  {
    question: "The book that deals with love between a man and woman is _____",
    options: ["Psalms", "Ecclesiastes", "Song of Solomon", "Proverbs"],
    answer: "Song of Solomon",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The commandment that requires humans to honor their father and mother is _____",
    options: [
      "the first commandment",
      "the fifth commandment",
      "the tenth commandment",
      "the second commandment",
    ],
    answer: "the fifth commandment",
  },
  {
    question: "The youngest son of Jacob was _____",
    options: ["Simeon", "Levi", "Benjamin", "Judah"],
    answer: "Benjamin",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The son of David who conspired to take over the throne was _____",
    options: ["Absalom", "Adonijah", "Solomon", "Amnon"],
    answer: "Adonijah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The people of Israel were warned by God about the consequences of idolatry through _____",
    options: ["the prophets", "the priests", "the judges", "the kings"],
    answer: "the prophets",
  },
  {
    question: "Jesus was tempted in the wilderness for _____",
    options: ["seven days", "forty days", "thirty days", "ten days"],
    answer: "forty days",
  },
  {
    question: "The wise man who built his house upon the rock is a _____",
    options: [
      "believer",
      "repentant sinner",
      "man of understanding",
      "wise servant",
    ],
    answer: "man of understanding",
  },
];
